Congratulations and thank you for getting to the end of this short course.
As we conclude the course, let's recap the main topics we covered.
We went over details of how an llm works, including subtleties like the tokenizer
and why it can't reverse lollipop.
We learned methods for evaluating user inputs to ensure the quality and safety
of the system, processing inputs using both chain of thought reasoning and
splitting tasks into subtasks with chain prompts and checking outputs
before showing them to users.
We also took a look at methods for evaluating the system over time, so as
to monitor and improve its performance.
Throughout the course, we also discussed the importance of building responsibly
with these tools, ensuring that the model is safe and provides appropriate
responses that are accurate, relevant, and in the tone you want.
As always, practice is key to mastering these concepts.
So we hope you'll apply what you've learned in your own projects.
And so that's it.
There are so many exciting applications that are yet to be built.
The world needs more people like you building useful applications, and we
look forward to hearing about the amazing things you build.