In this first video, I'd like to share with you an overview of how LLMs, large language
models work. We'll go into how they are trained as well as details like the tokenizer and how
that can affect the output of when you prompt an LLM. And we'll also take a look at the chat
format for LLMs, which is a way of specifying both system as well as user messages and understand
what you can do with that capability. Let's take a look. First, how does a large language model
work? You're probably familiar with the text generation process where you can give a prompt,
I love eating and ask an LLM to fill in what the things are likely completions given this prompt.
And it may say bagels with cream cheese or my mother's meatloaf or else with friends. But how
did the model learn to do this? The main tool used to train an LLM is actually supervised learning.
In supervised learning, a computer learns an input output or X or Y mapping using label training
data. So for example, if you're using supervised learning to learn to classify the sentiment of
restaurant reviews, you might collect a training set like this where a review like the best
Chinese sandwich is great is labeled as a positive sentiment review, and so on. And
service is slow, the food is so-so is negative, and the earl grey tea was fantastic as a positive
label. By the way, both Izer and I were born in the UK and so both of us like our earl grey tea.
And so the process for supervised learning is typically to get label data and then train a
model on data. And after training, you can then deploy and call the model and give it a new
restaurant review like best pizza I've ever had. You hopefully output that that has a positive
sentiment. It turns out that supervised learning is a core building block for training large
language models. Specifically, a large language model can be built by using supervised learning
to repeatedly predict the next word. Let's say that in your training sets of a lot of text data,
you have to sentence my favorite food is a bagel with cream cheese and mox.
Then this sentence is turned into a sequence of training examples where given a sentence fragment,
my favorite food is a, if you want to predict the next word in this case was bagel, or given the
sentence fragment or sentence prefix, my favorite food is a bagel. The next word in this case would
be with and so on. And given a large training sets of hundreds of billions or sometimes even
more words, you can then create a massive training set where you can start off with part of a
sentence or part of a piece of text and repeatedly ask the language model to learn to predict what
is the next word. So today there are broadly two major types of large language models.
The first is a base LLM and the second which is what is increasingly used is the instruction
to know. So the base LLM repeatedly predicts the next word based on text training data.
And so if I give it a prompt, once upon a time there was a unicorn, then it may by repeatedly
predicting one word at a time come up with a completion that tells a story about a unicorn
living in a magical forest with all unicorn friends. Now a downside of this is that if you
were to prompt it with what is the capital of France, quite plausible that on the internet
there might be a list of quiz questions about France. So it may complete this with what is
France's largest city, what is France's population and so on. But what you really want is you want
it to tell you what is the capital of France probably rather than list all these questions.
So an instruction to an LLM instead tries to follow instructions and will hopefully say
the capital of France is Paris. How do you go from a base LLM to an instruction to an LLM?
This is what the process of training an instruction to an LLM like ChatGPT looks like. You first
train a base LLM on a lot of data, so hundreds of billions of words, maybe even more. And this is a
process that can take months on a large supercomputing system. After you've trained the
base LLM, you would then further train the model by fine tuning it on a smaller set of examples
where the output follows an input instruction. And so for example, you may have contractors
help you write a lot of examples of an instruction and then a good response to an instruction.
And that creates a training set to carry out this additional fine tuning so that learns to predict
what is the next word if it's trying to follow an instruction. After that, to improve the quality
of the LLM's output, a common process now is to obtain human ratings of the quality
of many different LLM outputs on criteria such as whether the output is helpful, honest, and harmless.
And you can then further tune the LLM to increase the probability of its generating the more highly
rated outputs. And the most common technique to do this is RLHF, which stands for Reinforcement
Learning from Human Feedback. And whereas training the base LLM can take months, the process of
going from the base LLM to the instruction to an LLM can be done in maybe days on much more-
on a much more modest size data sets and much more modest size computational resources.
So this is how you would use an LLM. I'm going to import a few libraries. I'm going to load my
OpenAI key here. I'll say a little bit more about this later in this video. And here's a helper
function to get a completion given a prompt. If you have not yet installed the OpenAI package
on your computer, you might have to run pip install OpenAI, but I already have it installed
here, so I won't run that. And let me hit shift enter to run these. And now I can set response
equals get completion. What is the capital of France? And hopefully it will give me a good
result. Now, about- now, in the description of the large language model so far, I talked about it as
predicting one word at a time, but there's actually one more important technical detail.
If you were to tell it, take the letters in the word- word lollipop and reverse them.
This seems like an easy task. Maybe like a four-year-old could do this task. But if you were
to ask chatGPT to do this, it actually outputs a somewhat garbled whatever this is. This is not
L-O-L-I-P-L-P. This is not lollipop's letters reversed. So why is chatGPT unable to do what
seems like a relatively simple task? It turns out that there's one more important detail for how
a large language model works, which is it doesn't actually repeatedly predict the next word. It
instead repeatedly predicts the next token. And what an LLM actually does is it will take a
sequence of characters like learning new things is fun and group the characters together to form
tokens that comprise commonly occurring sequences of characters. So here, learning new things is
fun. Each of them is a fairly common word. And so each token corresponds to one word or one word
in a space or an exclamation mark. But if you were to give it input with some somewhat less
frequently used words like prompting is powerful developer to the word prompting is still not that
common in the English language, but certainly gaining in popularity. And so prompting is
actually broken down to three tokens with prompt and in because those three are commonly occurring
sequences of letters. And if you were to give it the word lollipop, the tokenizer actually breaks
this down into three tokens, L and O and Epop. And because Chai GPT isn't seeing the individual
letters is instead seeing these three tokens, it's more difficult for it to correctly print out
these letters in reverse order. So here's a trick you can use to fix this. If I were to add dashes
between these letters and spaces would work too or other things would work too
and tell it take the letters and lollipop and reverse them. Then it actually does a much
better job this OOIPOP. And the reason for that is if you pass it lollipop with dashes in between
the letters, it tokenizes each of these characters into an individual token, making it easier for it
to see the individual letters and print them out in reverse order. So if you ever want to use
Chai GPT to play a word game like Wordle or Scrabble or something, this nifty trick helps it to
better see the individual letters of the words. For the English language, one token roughly on
average corresponds to about four characters or about three quarters of a word. And so different
large language models will often have different limits on the number of input plus output tokens
it can accept. The input is often called the context and the output is often called the completion.
And the model GPT 3.5 Turbo, for example, the most commonly used Chai GPT model has a limit
of roughly 4,000 tokens in the input plus output. So if you try to feed it an input context that's
much longer than this, it'll actually throw an exception or generate an error. Next, I want to
share with you another powerful way to use an LLM API, which involves specifying separate system,
user and assistant messages. Let me show you an example, then we can explain in more detail
what it's actually doing. Here's a new helper function called getCompletionFromMessages.
And when we prompt this LLM, we are going to give it multiple messages. Here's an example
of what you can do. I'm going to specify first a message in the role of a system. So this
assistant message and the content of the system messages, you're an assistant who responds in
the style of Dr. Seuss. Then I'm going to specify a user message. So the role of the second message
is role user. And the content of this is write me a very short poem about a happy carrot. And
so let's run that. And with temperature equals one, I actually never know what's going to come
out. But okay, that's a cool poem. Oh, how jolly is this carrot that I see? And it actually rhymes
pretty well. All right, well done, chatGPT. And so in this example, the system message specifies
the overall tone of what you want the large language model to do. And the user message is
a specific instruction that you wanted to carry out, given this higher level behavior that was
specified in the system message. Here's an illustration of how it all works. So this is
how the chat format works. The system message sets the overall tone of behavior of the large language
model or the assistant. And then when you give the user message, such as maybe, such as a tell
me a joke or write me a poem, it will then output an appropriate response following what you asked
for in the user message and consistence with the overall behavior set in the system message.
And by the way, although I'm not illustrating it here, if you want to use this in a multi-term
conversation, you can also input assistant messages in this messages format to let chatGPT
know what it had previously said. If you wanted to continue the conversation based on things that
had previously said as well. But here are a few more examples. If you want to set the tone to
tell it to have a one sentence long output, then in the system message, I can say all your responses
must be one sentence long. And when I execute this, it outputs a single sentence. It's no longer
a poem, not in the style of Dr. Seuss, but it's a single sentence. There's a story about the happy
carrot. And if we want to combine both specify the style and the length, then I can use the system
message to say, in the system response to style Dr. Seuss, all your sentences must be one sentence long.
And now this generates a nice one sentence poem. It was always smiling and never scary. I like that.
That's a very happy poem. And then lastly, just for fun, if you are using an LLM and you want to
know how many tokens are you using, here's a helper function that is a little bit more sophisticated
in that it gets a response from the open AI API endpoint. And then it uses other values in the
response to tell you how many prompt tokens, completion tokens, and total tokens were used in your API call.
Let me define that. And if I run this now, here's the response. And here is
a count of how many tokens we use. So this output, which had 55 tokens, whereas the prompt input had
37 tokens. So this used up 92 tokens altogether. When I'm using LLM models in practice, I don't
worry that much, frankly, about the number of tokens I'm using. Maybe one case where it might
be worth checking the number of tokens is if you're worried that the user might have given
you too long an input that exceeds the 4,000 or so token limits of Chai GPT, in which case you
could double check how many tokens it was and truncate it to make sure you're staying within
the input token limits of the large language model. Now, I want to share with you one more tip for how
to use a large language model. Calling the open AI API requires using an API key that's tied to
either a free or a paid account. And so many developers will write the API key in plain text
like this into their Jupyter notebook. And this is a less secure way of using API keys that I would
not recommend you use, because it's just too easy to share this notebook with someone else or check
this into GitHub or something, and thus end up leaking your API key to someone else. In contrast,
what you saw me do in the Jupyter notebook was this piece of code where I use a library
.env and then run this command load.env find.env to read a local file which is called.env that
contains my secret key. And so with this code snippet, I have locally stored a file called
.env that contains my API key, and this loads it into the operating systems environmental variable.
And then os.getenv, open AI API key stores it into this variable. And in this whole process,
I don't ever have to enter the API key in plain text and unencrypted plain text into my Jupyter
notebook. So this is a relatively more secure and a better way to access the API key. And in fact,
this is a general method for storing different API keys from lots of different online services
that you might want to use and call from a Jupyter notebook. Lastly, I think the degree to which
prompting is revolutionizing AI application development is still underappreciated. In the
traditional supervised machine learning workflow, like the restaurant review sentiment classification
example that I touched on just now, if you want to build a classifier to classify restaurant review
positive and negative sentiments, you at first get a bunch of label data, maybe hundreds of examples.
This might take, I don't know, weeks, maybe a month. Then you would train a model on data and
getting an appropriate open source model, tuning on the model, evaluating it. That might take days,
weeks, maybe even a few months. And then you might have to find a cloud service to deploy it,
and then get your model uploaded to the cloud and then run the model and finally be able to call
your model. And that's again, not uncommon for this to take a team a few months to get working.
In contrast with prompting based machine learning, when you have a text application,
you can specify a prompt. This can take minutes, maybe hours if you need to iterate a few times
to get an effective prompt. And then in hours, maybe at most days, but frankly, more often hours,
you can have this running using API calls and start making calls to the model. And once you've
done that in just again, maybe minutes or hours, you can start calling the model and start making
inferences. And so there are applications that used to take me maybe six months or a year to build
that you can now build in minutes or hours, maybe very small numbers of days using prompting. And
this is revolutionizing what AI applications can be built quickly. One important caveat,
this applies to many unstructured data applications, including specifically text
applications and maybe increasingly vision applications, although the vision technology is
much less mature right now, but it's kind of getting there. This recipe doesn't really work
for structured data applications, meaning machine learning applications on tabular data with lots of
numerical values in Excel spreadsheets, hey? But for applications to which this does apply,
the fact that AI components can be built so quickly is changing the workflow of how the
entire system might be built. Building an entire system might still take days or weeks or something,
but at least this piece of it can be done much faster. And so with that, let's go on to the next
video where Yisa will show how to use these components to evaluate the input to a customer
service assistant. And this will be part of a bigger example that you see developed through
this course for building a customer service assistant for an online retailer.